Guide to the Susan Cataldo Papers MSS.194
Fales Library and Special Collections
Susan Cataldo Papers
1977-2003
1982-1999
Fales Library and Special Collections
Cataldo, Susan, 1952-2001
Spicehandler, Stephen
MSS.194
6.75 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons; 2 manuscript boxes; 1 flat box, and 1 CD box
2,000 Megabytes in 3 CD-Rs
Susan Cataldo (1952-2001) was an American poet and published author. She spent most of her adult life living in the East Village in Manhattan and was involved with the Poetry Project at St. Mark's Church. This collection highlights Cataldo's career as a writer in New York City during the 1980s and 1990s. Materials include newsletters, poems, writings, manuscripts, notebooks, letters, diaries, print publications and three CD-Rs that feature recordings of Cataldo at the Poetry Project during the 1980s.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restricitions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Stephen Spicehandler in 2006; additional materials were donated in 2010. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2007.194 and 2010.194.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged in the order in which they were received by donor.
Biographical Note
Susan Cataldo was born in the Bronx, New York on September 15, 1952. She spent most of her adult life living in the East Village in Manhattan and first became involved with the Poetry Project at St. Mark's Church in the late 1970s, where she participated in and lead writing workshops. Cataldo published three books of poems including "Brooklyn-Queens Day," "The Mother Journal," and "drenched." Her work has appeared in numerous poetry publications and anthologies. Cataldo passed away on April 25, 2001 from ovarian cancer.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
Materials include monthly literary newsletters that Cataldo subscribed to; her original poems and writings; draft manuscripts of Cataldo's work; personal notebooks from different workshops and classes; sketchbooks with her drawings; letters from other poets and writers; personal diaries; copies of her published works, including the book, "drenched," that was published after her death in 2002; and three CD-Rs that feature recordings of Cataldo at The Poetry Project at St. Mark's Church during the 1980s. The bulk of the collection consists of Cataldo's personal diaries that include her thoughts, notes, sketches, and poems between 1977 and 2000. One diary in particular, located in box 2, contains Cataldo's poetry that was published in her work, "Mother Journal."
Downtown Collection.; Downtown writers.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Spicehandler, Stephen
- Poems and resume, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Grave du Nord, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- New Alternatives for Children, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Publications and manuscripts, 1999, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Metropolis, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- The Mother Journal, 2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
- Poetry, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Journal [manuscripts], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Poetry and writings, 1979-1999, undated (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
- We are Integrated and Wonderfully Made, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Brooklyn Queens Day, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Poetry, 2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Poetry [and writings], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Spicehandler, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Poetry and writings, 1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Forty, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Poetry, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Loose material, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Diaries, 1977-1995, undated (Box 1, Box 2)
- Susan Cataldo introduced by Jim Brodey 12/23/1981; The Poetry Project at St. Mark's Church [CD-R] (Box Shared Fales 007)
- Susan Cataldo introduced by Bernadette Mayer 12/15/84; The Poetry Project at St. Mark's Chruch [CD-R], 1984 (Box Shared Fales 007)
- Susan Cataldo introduced by Ed Friedman 1/27/1988; The Poetry Project at St. Mark's Church [CD-R] (Box Shared Fales 007)
- Diary, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Current [poetry and writings], 1991-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Writing I don't throw out for many different reasons [poetry and writings], 1981-1992, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Steve Spicehandler, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Diaries, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
- Metropolis, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- The World, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Caveman, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Letters, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Diaries, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Born Yesterday, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Poems not in manuscript, 1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Tamarind, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Panda Heart by Jim Brodey, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Tamarind, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- The World, circa 1982 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Panda Heart by Jim Brodey, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Poetry Project, 1990-1995 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Tamarind, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- The World, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Born Yesterday, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Poetry, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
- "drenched: selected poems by Susan Cataldo", 2003 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Panda Heart by Jim Brodey, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Diaries and sketch books, 1985-2000 (Box 4)
- Sketches, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Loose sketches from Swathmore sketch book, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Sketch books, undated (Box 5)
- Print publications, 1981-2003 (Box 6)
- Little Light, issues 1-6, 1980-1984 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
- The Word, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Autobiographical Short Story Writing - Oct '89 - Jan '90, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Correspondence from Greg Masters, poet, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Correspondence from Eileen Myles, poet, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Correspondence from Bob Herson, poet/publisher, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Correspondence from Robert Creely, poet, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Correspondence from Gillian McCain, poet/author, circa 1995 - circa 1998 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Correspondence from Lillian Abel, painter, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Correspondence from Eric Holzman, painter, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Correspondence from Rochelle Kraut, poet, 1984-1993 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Correspondence from John Godfrey, poet, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Correspondence from Peggy De Coursey, confidante/friend to many poets, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Correspondence from Hannah Weiner, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, circa 1985 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Correspondence from Charlotte Carter, author, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Correspondence from Maureen Owen, poet, 1982-1994 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Correspondence from Danny Krakauer poet, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Correspondence from Douglas Oliver, poet, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Correspondence from Ed Friedman, poet, 1989-1994 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Correspondence from Jim Brodey, poet, 1985-1997 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Correspondence from Power Boothe, theatre [sic] artist, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Correspondence from Susan Barnes, painter, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Notes from Harrris Schiff, poet/teacher, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Correspondence from Alice Notley, poet, 1995-1998 (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Correspondence from Simon Pettet, poet, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Correspondence from Susan Timmons, poet, 1993-1995 (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Correspondence from Gary Lenhart, poet, 1980-1995 (Box 6, Folder 29)
- Print Publications, 1982-1984 (Box 6, Folder 30-33)
- Copy of Franny Winston, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Sketchbooks, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Miscellaneous writing (finished and unfinished), 1977-1979, undated (Box 6, Folder 37)
- Diary, circa 1983 (Box 6, Folder 36)
- Clippings, flyer, 1980, undated (Box 6, Folder 38)
- Letters and poetry, 1992, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Print publications, 1979-1992, undated (Box 7, Folder 2-6, Box 8, Folder 1-5)